<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>My Blog</title>
  <subtitle>I am writing about stuff.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://example.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://example.com/"/>
  <updated>2024-04-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://example.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Your Name</name>
    <email>me@example.com</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Engineering Capstone - C3 SD File System and Screen File Editor</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2024/04/12/capstone/"/>
    <updated>2024-04-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2024/04/12/capstone/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is a recap of my capstone project for my computer engineering degree.
It will include many contents from the final report I wrote for the capstone as well as some of my own experiences over the 4 months we worked on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my capstone, my group partnered with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elevenengineering.com/&quot;&gt;Eleven Engineering Inc&lt;/a&gt;.
Eleven Engineering Inc is a company based out of Edmonton, AB that focuses on semiconductors for wireless audio applications primarily.
Notably, they have created the &amp;quot;XInC2&amp;quot; processor - a multithreaded RISC-based 16-bit processor designed for their wireless audio applications.
At some point in time, Eleven Engineering collaborated with my university and gave them the rights to use their XInC2 CPU in electrical engineering capstone projects to &amp;quot;give back&amp;quot; to my university&#39;s community.
This resulted in a project called the &amp;quot;C3 board&amp;quot; (standing for &amp;quot;Credit Card Computer&amp;quot;) - a single-board computer similar to a Raspberry Pi, but powered by the XInC2 CPU.
Effectively, it&#39;s an all-Canadian-made SBC, which is pretty fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as with any new computer system, the C3 board lacks a comprehensive software ecosystem.
The board is currently (as of 2024) extremely barebones - it lacks an operating system, and only the low-level driver code needed for bare minimum functionality exists.
If the goal of the C3 board is to be as versatile as similar boards like the Raspberry Pi, then it needs a solid software foundation in order to provide a wide range of functionality to users.
This is where my capstone comes into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My capstone group worked with Eleven Engineering as well as my university to develop two major components of the software ecosystem for the C3 board.
The first of the two is an &lt;strong&gt;SD Card File System&lt;/strong&gt;, which enables the board to interface with SD cards stored in the board&#39;s SD slot.
This gives the board the ability to read from and write to files, which greatly enhances its functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other project, and the one I had more of a direct hand in the development in, is called the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;Screen File Editor&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;.
It&#39;s a term coined by Eleven Engineering in the proposal documentation given to us that refers to a text-editor-like program that runs on the C3 board.
Specifically, it is designed to run with hardware specifically designed for the C3 board to allow you to edit files on the board without an external computer, at least when used in conjunction with the SD File System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also mention that we weren&#39;t the only capstone group to work with the C3 board. There were two other groups to my knowledge, who worked on equally interesting projects such as a Python interpreter and some enhanced low-level routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>This Website (Old)</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2023/04/12/this-website/"/>
    <updated>2023-04-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2023/04/12/this-website/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a small article to document this website and its creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;int main() {
    printf(&amp;quot;lmao now give me coder&amp;quot;);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this &lt;strong&gt;cool&lt;/strong&gt; image I generated using Bing Image Creator!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://example.com/posts/2023/04/12/sands.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sand&quot; style=&quot;width: 40em&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Red Sands](../sands.jpg) --&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ice Cream - A Discord Bot (Ongoing)</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2023/01/28/ice-cream-bot/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2023/01/28/ice-cream-bot/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Unlike my first Discord bot, &amp;quot;Ice Cream Bot&amp;quot; is the name of the first Discord bot I&#39;ve started writing that intends to actually be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Luster - A Dating Website (ShellHacks 2022 Entry)</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2022/09/11/luster-dating-site/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2022/09/11/luster-dating-site/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Luster is a dating app created for the 2022 ShellHacks hackathon. I participated in a group consisting of myself and 4 other programmers to see what we could come up with in 48 hours. Since the project was an extremely ambitious idea for a hackathon, we were not able to finish everything we hoped to achieve with it. However, we may continue developing it in the future for the sake of completeness.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>PyTerminal</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2022/09/22/pyterminal/"/>
    <updated>2022-09-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2022/09/22/pyterminal/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyTerminal originally started as an experiment following some work I did at one of my previous internships.
In the internship, I was tasked with writing a program from scratch using Python and Qt to control a mechanical device through an Arduino and some control circuitry.
When I wrote this application, one of the features I included was a terminal that printed the different motor commands out in the GUI for the user to debug if needed.
This feature left me wondering what other ways you could use Qt to make terminal-like applications, and it ultimately led to me trying to figure out if a full terminal emulator was possible to write.
PyTerminal &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; that terminal emulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realistically, this program &lt;strong&gt;sucks&lt;/strong&gt; and you should not use this in any real capacity.
It is very buggy, adds no meaningful features over other terminal emulators and is just slow in general.
I created it to prove a point about the simplest possible way to create a terminal emulator.
It should be very obvious that any terminal emulator written in Python is probably not one you want to use, but in case it wasn&#39;t obvious, there you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Zgell/pyterminal&quot;&gt;A link to the code can be found here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Stream Schedule Generator</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2022/08/02/stream-schedule-gen/"/>
    <updated>2022-09-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2022/08/02/stream-schedule-gen/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a friend who streams regularly on Twitch. He plays a variety of video games on his stream. To let his audience know what he plans to stream for the week, he puts out a schedule each week to let his audience know what to expect.
These schedules came in the form of a sort of infographic that he would post in his Discord server. He used to make these schedules manually each week and would spend 20-30 minutes on each one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After talking about his schedules with him, I got the idea to try and write a program for him that would automate the heavy lifting of making these schedules. The key requirements were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The program has to make it easier/faster to create the schedules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup has to be very simple: as simple as running the program and entering in the information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has to be able to show the box art of the game(s) schedule for the week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has to be able to produce an image that&#39;s good to go as-is (ie. no other steps).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was a success! The program can create an entire schedule in about 15 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interacts with IGDB API to get the box art of any game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses a template image I created from old schedules and fills them out with box art from IGDB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Written in Python, but I used Py2EXE to convert it into a standalone EXE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Node-based Dialogue System in Rust</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2022/07/27/node-dialogue/"/>
    <updated>2022-07-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2022/07/27/node-dialogue/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Really, this project was just an excuse to learn Rust. Rust is such a cool programming language to me, but admittedly I don&#39;t have a lot of uses for it yet. Around the time I wanted to learn Rust, I also was thinking about interesting ways to structure dialog in RPG video games. I envisioned a system that used a type of &amp;quot;dynamic&amp;quot; dialog that changed in response to the way the user interacts with the NPC. I thought that the best way to do this was a tree-style system that uses a variety of types of nodes to control the flow of dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was really interesting to implement in Rust because the way Rust handles object-oriented style programming is very different. Instead of classes and subclasses, Rust uses a struct system that is similar to C, but also has &amp;quot;traits&amp;quot; that fill in some of the missing object-oriented stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Raytracer</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2021/06/26/raytracer/"/>
    <updated>2022-07-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2021/06/26/raytracer/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This project is a modified version of the raytracing program in Peter Shirley&#39;s &amp;quot;Raytracing in One Weekend&amp;quot; book. I was interested in following along with this tutorial to learn more about the raytracing algorithm as well as keep my C++ skills sharp. Following along one-for-one with the tutorial was nice, but I wanted to make a modified version with some performance optimizations, so that&#39;s what I did.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Game of Life V3: JavaScript Edition</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2021/03/26/game-of-life-js/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2021/03/26/game-of-life-js/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following my previous two attempts at implementing John Conway&#39;s Game of Life, I felt a little disappointed with the lack of interactivity with the game. It always looks like so much fun to be able to directly modify the board. Also, you can search online and find lots of discovered shapes that people have found that have certain behaviors, and it&#39;s fascinating to me that such shapes have been found. I wanted a version of the game that let you experiment with these patterns for yourself. Around this time, I was also learning a library known as &amp;quot;p5.js&amp;quot;, which lets you create interactive canvases in JavaScript. This led to the major idea of this project: implement the Game of Life as a p5.js canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Game of Life V2: Python Edition</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2020/05/15/game-of-life-python/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2020/05/15/game-of-life-python/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An expanded version of the quick program I wrote in MATLAB with a few new features.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>COVID-19 Statistics Web Scraper</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2020/05/03/covid-web-scraper/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2020/05/03/covid-web-scraper/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a small Python program I wrote during the beginning of the pandemic right after my school year had ended. This was when the COVID-19 lockdowns were in full effect and people couldn&#39;t do much. I decided to spend my time cooped up in my home learning some new programming tricks, and for this project, the focus was on web scraping.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Expansion of my Perceptron Program in C++</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2020/04/15/nn-cpp/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2020/04/15/nn-cpp/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A rewrite of my MATLAB neural network in C++ with some extended features.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Conway&#39;s Game of Life - MATLAB Edition</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2020/04/05/game-of-life-matlab/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2020/04/05/game-of-life-matlab/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A quick script I created to recreate the popular cellular automaton, &amp;quot;Game of Life&amp;quot; by mathematician John Conway.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Engineering Computer Programming Contest Entry - Evolution &amp; Environment Simulator</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2020/04/01/encmp-100/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2020/04/01/encmp-100/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Intro to the EMCMP 100 Contest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole project started in my second semester of my first year of engineering. One of the courses that we are required to take in the first year is called &amp;quot;ENCMP 100&amp;quot;, or &amp;quot;Programming for Engineers&amp;quot;. I was pretty excited about taking this course since I had a background in programming and thoroughly enjoyed the subject. However, since the course was geared towards newcomers to the programming scene, I found it very difficult to be engaged with the material. It was really hard learning about basic programming concepts that I have known about for years. I found myself getting really far ahead in the course material, sometimes by as much as 2 months. But, all of this changed one day in January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My professor announced that later in the course there would be an optional programming contest that was tied to the course. Given that I found all of the assignments pretty easy, I was intrigued because I wanted a challenge. In early February, all of the details of the contest were released, and we were given about a week to sign up for it. I decided to go for it because it was going to be a new and interesting experience for me. Although I had spent a lot of time programming for personal projects, I had never really shared anything I did because I wasn&#39;t confident enough in my abilities to program and not get scrutinized for a lack of programming skill in the eyes of others. With that considered, jumping all the way to a programming competition was quite a stretch, and so I made sure to give it everything I had in order to have a chance at winning. I felt like the competition would give myself the opportunity to prove to others, but even more importantly myself, that I could make something good if I really applied myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a bit of background, the competition worked like this. You would register before the end of the first week of February, and then you would have until March 27th to code the program. You had to document your process because one of the criteria for judging competition entries was the process (ex. if you left the whole project to the end of March, you wouldn&#39;t score well). They wanted students to spread out the workload fairly evenly. You were also allowed to have 1 partner, but no groups larger than 2. You also had to produce a video showing off your project, the timeline for it, and other details relating to it. This was also a very important criterion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided early on that I wanted to find a partner for this competition because I felt like with how busy I got with school, I needed an additional person to keep me responsible for completing it. It would also be good to have an extra set of hands working on it as it would speed up some of the optimization processes and would also help me overcome particularly troublesome hurdles in the code. I knew a guy who lived on the same floor as myself in my residence building who liked to program as well, and so he was ultimately the one I entered the competition with. I remember that he wasn&#39;t really confident that he could contribute to the competition because he didn&#39;t have as much experience as I did, but I had a feeling that we would both be carrying our own weight for this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://example.com/posts/2020/04/01/resultsmenu.png&quot; alt=&quot;Program Output&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;display: block; width: 50%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
A picture of the window that pops up at the end of the program&#39;s run time. It displays four different plots which all contain information pertaining to the environment. The user can extrapolate correlations between the user-specified inputs and these outputs by comparison.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- *A picture of the window that pops up at the end of the program&#39;s run time. It displays four different plots which all contain information pertaining to the environment. The user can extrapolate correlations between the user-specified inputs and these outputs by comparison.* --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also had to decide what we wanted to do for our project. Our first ideas involved working with neural networks, as I had finished the MATLAB neural network project shortly before the competition details were released. Despite being really interested in neural networks, I didn&#39;t really want this to be our project for a few reasons. Firstly, I knew that the project would either be way too easy or way too hard, and would not be within a reasonable range of difficulty. We would either end up using MATLAB&#39;s Deep Learning Toolbox, which would make a neural network project just a little bit too simple and not complicated enough for the scope of the competition. Or, we could program the framework of the neural network from the ground up similar to what I did in my project, but this would be too difficult to implement in a meaningful way that has a result we could actually show off that isn&#39;t just abstract numbers and other gibberish. On top of that, we didn&#39;t really know what we wanted to apply a neural network to. It would have to be something interesting and easy to show off so that the graders would be interested in it, but we didn&#39;t have any ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came up with the idea that eventually became the project from a combination of two things. First of all, I saw a similar idea in a video on YouTube about someone creating a project that simulates natural selection. I thought that the idea was pretty interesting, and I ended up mentioning it in a conversation later with both my partner and a computer science student who also lived on my floor. We were hanging out in the floor lounge talking about programming stuff, and I brought up the project I saw on YouTube. The computer science student said that he was thinking of making something similar, and my contest partner thought it was interesting. We talked about different twists you could take on the project, and an interesting idea that came up was an evolution simulator. This was ultimately what my partner and I chose, as it felt both complex enough to score well in the competition but not too difficult to achieve within the span of about two months. We also felt that it would be an adequate use for the MATLAB language, as MATLAB exceeds in data visualization and it was fitting to have a highly data-oriented project to go with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Planning and Theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first thing we had to decide when we began the project is what we actually wanted to achieve with it. This was pretty straightforward, and all we had to do was organize these ideas. The primary ideas that we set as targets for the project were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predators (that would eat the animals)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naturally-occurring food (to keep the animals alive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reproduction (so that populations could sustain themselves)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mortality (so that populations would not grow indefinitely and be properly constrained by the rules of life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genetics (so that the animal populations could adapt and become better at surviving in their environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-time visualization of the environment (so you could see what was happening)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal on the above list that we started with was actually the visualization aspect of the project. At the time we were both still very new to MATLAB, and we weren&#39;t familiar with the extent of MATLAB&#39;s data visualization features. We began by exploring these features to see how we were going to visualize any number of moving entities in real time. We quickly discovered the &lt;code&gt;image&lt;/code&gt; function, which took a matrix as an input and created a figure that displayed it. This function was useful because there were a few interesting things that we could do with it. First of all, we could resize the window to our liking using MATLAB&#39;s &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; function, despite the fact that the &lt;code&gt;image&lt;/code&gt; function itself didn&#39;t appear to have that as a built-in feature. As the figure produced was a bit small, we figured that this would be mandatory for a satisfactory user experience. Secondly, if we were to change a value in the matrix and then call the &lt;code&gt;image&lt;/code&gt; function again, it would keep the current figure window open and just update the matrix. This was really useful because it allowed us to animate the matrix, which meant that we could use it as a sort of screen for all the action inside of the simulation. It also updated surprisingly fast, which made it viable for real-time simulation as well. Finally, one last nice feature MATLAB has for data visualization is the ability to create custom colour maps for the data in the matrix. This would allow us to fine-tune what every number in the matrix corresponded to on the map and would give us full visual control over the elements of the simulation, at least in terms of colour. As an added bonus, we could also use the &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; function to change the title of the plot as well as the title of the window. This did end up being our method of visualization, and it worked well throughout the production of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we solved the environment visualization problem, the next goal we tackled was the genetics system. We didn&#39;t necessarily implement it in a practical way right off the start since we didn&#39;t even have the bases for the animals in yet, but we were approaching it from a more abstract, mathematical approach. We wanted to find a way to express the dominance of genes and their overlapping behaviour during reproduction as mathematical equations that MATLAB would be able to understand. We also wanted to tailor the equations specifically for the simulator so that we would observe the perfect amount of genetic variation in the simulator as the generations went on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Timeline and Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the big challenges we faced all throughout the span of the project was the optimization of the code. Our project idea was already an uphill battle because of how complex it was, but on top of that, we had to do it in MATLAB, which is a very slow programming language. This made good optimization of the system absolutely essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that my partner and I spent quite a bit of time on was the analysis of how MATLAB handled different data types, and how using certain types would affect processing speed. Fortunately, one really nice feature of MATLAB is the &lt;code&gt;tic&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;toc&lt;/code&gt; functions, which start and end a timer respectively. This allowed us to benchmark the effects of working with certain data types in mass down to the millisecond, which helped with determining the fastest way to compute the simulation. MATLAB has a number of integer and double variants that each consume a different amount of memory and also have a different level of accuracy. We found that the difference between lower and higher memory decimal values was almost negligible, and that we actually lost more performance converting different data types than we gained from using singles as opposed to doubles in our computation. A workaround was to initialize certain values as singles and others as doubles, and this did actually work as long as there were no interactions between the two categories, which we minimized for the simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion and Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key takeaways from this whole project, at least for me, was the importance of good program structure in bigger projects. This was one of the first big coding projects that I had completed, and so a lot of features that I normally would not have to implement (ie. several different OOP classes and structures). We originally began the project without too much structure, with the only classes in the project being that of the animals and the predators. However, once we began to implement some of the more complex features such as resources and reproduction, we quickly realized that we were going to need to restructure the program to make some of the calculations work. By adding a controller class to handle a lot of the repetitive computations, it made the whole process a lot smoother. We likely would not have finished the project if we hadn&#39;t included that class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all this, we got an email back from the competition coordinator about 2 weeks after we sent it our submission. He responded to us to tell us that we actually won 1st place in the contest with our submission, which was a really exciting moment for the both of us. I had never entered a programming competition before and I had always been too self-conscious about my programming skills to enter anything serious in the case that it was way over my level of programming knowledge and that I wouldn&#39;t be able to do anything useful. I think that this competition greatly improved my confidence in my programming abilities and made me way less scared of sharing my ideas with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Download and Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run this program, open &lt;code&gt;main.m&lt;/code&gt; in MATLAB (version 2019b or later) and run that script. Make sure the rest of the files are in the same folder so the script can access them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://example.com/posts/2020/04/01/startmenu.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial Menu&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;display: block; width: 50%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
A picture of the first screen that shows up when you launch the &lt;code&gt;main.m&lt;/code&gt; file.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you run the program, you&#39;ll be met with an interface that looks like this. There&#39;s a number of parameters that users can change in order to play around with the outcome of the simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environment Size&lt;/strong&gt; - This parameter controls the size of the area that the animals can move around in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number of Animals&lt;/strong&gt; - The initial count of prey in the environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number of Predators&lt;/strong&gt; - The initial count of predators in the environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number of Steps&lt;/strong&gt; - The duration of the simulation. The program uses a step-based system that updates up to 200 times a second (although it never actually reaches that maximum due to how slow the MATLAB language is).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food Multiplier&lt;/strong&gt; - A multiplying factor that controls the amount of food introduced into the environment per iteration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food Frequency Multiplier&lt;/strong&gt; - A multiplying factor that scales how frequently food is introduced into the environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://example.com/posts/2020/04/01/helpmenu.png&quot; alt=&quot;Help Menu&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;display: block; width: 50%; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
A screenshot of the help page, which is more or less a repeat of what is written above.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also created a help page for users to have an in-application explanation of all of the factors. This wasn&#39;t a feature that we planned to add but after we started adding the different parameters that could affect the simulation, we realized that the program was very complex and unintuitive for other users. So I used the help page as an opportunity to practice interfaces in MATLAB while also adding a useful feature for understanding the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you&#39;ve set your parameters, click the &amp;quot;Start&amp;quot; button on the main page. What you&#39;ll be met with is a window that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://example.com/posts/2020/04/01/environmentmenu.png&quot; alt=&quot;Environment Menu&quot; style=&quot;width: 33%; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image above is an active display of everything that is occurring in the environment. It is a matrix whose size is determined by the size parameter set in the first menu. You can also see the duration of the simulation (controlled by the step number parameter) in the top of the window. Each coloured pixel represents something in the environment according to the guide below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;[Colour of Square on Grid]&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;[What it Represents]&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Black&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nothing present in that area of the environment.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;White&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;An animal (prey).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Red&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;An animal (predator).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Blue&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Food (for the prey to eat).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pink&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;An animal (prey) that is mature and seeking a partner to have offspring with.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dark Red&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;An animal (predator) that is mature and seeking a partner to have offspring with.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The display is programmed to update up to 200 times per second, which may sound like a lot until you realize that it will never come even close to that number in practice. The speed of MATLAB is one of the main reasons for that, as discussed in the challenges section.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://example.com/posts/2020/04/01/results.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Help Menu&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the simulation is complete, you will be met with a screen like what you see above. This will allow you to extrapolate the general behaviour of the simulation with your preferred settings.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Basic Perceptron from Scratch</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2020/01/23/basic-nn/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2020/01/23/basic-nn/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although this project is a bit of a strange one given that it was made in MATLAB and not a more appropriate programming language, there are a lot of things that led me to making this. I was looking for a more challenging project to create with MATLAB so I could further refine my skills with it. I wanted to explore the world of neural networks a bit further and expand my understanding of the core mechanics behind them. Although the project was started and finished across the span of 4 days, this project took a long time. In those 4 days I probably spent 2-4 hours a day working on it on average. There was a ridiculous amount of troubleshooting I had to go through, that I will elaborate on a bit later. But after a lot of work, I got what appears to be a functional product that passed the test I set for it. I have not implemented this model on a larger scale as of yet, and I am not sure if it would even be worth it to attempt to scale it up. Overall, the project served as an interesting learning experience and as an interesting visualization of the internal mathematics of basic neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pokemon Teambuilder Algorithm</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2020/01/17/pkmn-teambuilder/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2020/01/17/pkmn-teambuilder/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was my first attempt at an algorithm that I still, to this day, have yet to see a proper implementation of. I&#39;ve always had the idea of a smart tool that competitive Pokemon players could use to design a team that would have good synergy, and this algorithm was a very primitive attempt at generating good type matchups for a team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, I&#39;d like to revisit this program using either machine learning techniques or some kind of genetic algorithm. I can absolutely see how a genetic algorithm could be used to determine team typing in a way that generates teams that have very few weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pi Approximator</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2020/01/16/pi-approx/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2020/01/16/pi-approx/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This project began shortly after I started my ENCMP 100 (or Engineering Computer Programming) course in university. The programming language used in the course is MATLAB, a math-focused language that I unfortunately had no prior experience with. Given this lack of experience, I decided that doing a few extra projects on top of my coding assignments might be a fun idea that would also give me enough experience with MATLAB to enter the faculty&#39;s programming competition. This particular script is the very first project I started and finished in MATLAB. It isn&#39;t too complex or interesting, but I learned a lot about some of the mathematical theories regarding the approximation of pi while trying to make this.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Small EMP Device</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2019/04/30/emp/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2019/04/30/emp/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, this project was actually built specifically for my senior-year physics class in high school.
We were learning about electricity and magnetism at the time, and my physics teacher was always fond of hands-on projects for the sake of learning.
My teacher proposed that we get into groups of three, and build ourselves a basic speaker as a project.
My group wasn&#39;t very interested in this project, so we asked for permission to do a different project that still demonstrated an understanding of electricity and magnetism.
After a bit of discussion, we settled on building a small EMP device.
I had seen YouTube videos at the time of people building low-power EMP devices at their own with (mostly) common parts and I was fascinated with it.
Doing this as a project gave me an excuse to order all the parts and really give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been a long time since I worked on this project (I am currently writing this in 2024) so I don&#39;t have many of the initial designs.
However, I do remember the key components and how I worked with them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 4.5V power source (consisting of three AA batteries and a battery pack)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A (very sketchy) transformer that scaled up the 4.5V to a nominal 30kV (more on this later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A custom-made spark gap to create pulses of high current&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A coil of magnet wire wrapped around an iron core to produce magnetic fields&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle that this device operated on was that &lt;strong&gt;the ionization of air creates temporary high-current pulses&lt;/strong&gt; that can create short-lived but powerful magnetic fields that can disrupt low-power electronics.
The circuitry in the device is dedicated to making these current pulses, and the magnetic coil is what turns these current pulses into magnetic field pulses.
The way the circuit works is that a small voltage is applied to the input of the transformer, which creates a high-voltage-but-low-current output.
To transform the high voltage into a momentary high current, a spark gap is employed. The idea is that if enough voltage builds up on one side of the spark gap, it can cause the air between the two electrodes to temporarily ionize.
Air has a very high electrical resistance (about 30kΩ/cm if I remember correctly) but when ionized, has a very low electrical resistance.
This makes the spark gap behave like an electrical component that can switch between a very high and very low resistance, which allows for it to switch between ~0 mA and a very high current.
When that very high current is fed into a coil of wire, the resulting magnetic fields would (hopefully) be strong enough to observe disruption in other nearby electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some tuning of the width of the spark gap, I was able to get it to consistently disrupt the functionality of low-power electronic calculators.
When placed near these calculators, the voltage induced in the calculators&#39; circuitry caused &amp;quot;ghost keystrokes&amp;quot; where numbers were being entered into the calculator&#39;s memory without the buttons being physically pressed.
It was also able to disrupt the LCD screen and make it display invalid characters when the coil was placed on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the project was a success! I even got a 100% for the project in my physics class too. My physics teacher was very impressed with the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I didn&#39;t like about the project is that I never got to make a proper casing for the EMP device. I had designed the &amp;quot;guts&amp;quot; of the device, and they worked, but there was no nice container for it all.
I was trying to design a handheld device that contains all the parts but couldn&#39;t finalize a design ahead of the project&#39;s deadline, so I just had to demonstrate a video of the working prototype working at my house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also recognize that this was a somewhat dangerous project with the open spark gap and all that.
I wasn&#39;t too concerned with it at the time because even though the device looks and sounds scary when in operation, given the low power source I figured it wouldn&#39;t be fatal.
If I were to ever do a V2 of this project, I would for sure enclose that spark gap so that it doesn&#39;t pose any sort of risk.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>My First Discord Bot (&quot;StalinBot&quot;)</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2018/10/first-discord-bot/"/>
    <updated>2018-10-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2018/10/first-discord-bot/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My first Discord bot, or &amp;quot;StalinBot&amp;quot;, is a Discord bot I wrote for the purpose of terrorizing my friends on our preferred platform of communication, Discord.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>AlphaBot Control Program</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2018/06/03/alphabot/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2018/06/03/alphabot/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While this isn&#39;t the first robotics project I&#39;ve tackled throughout my life, this one is probably the most impressive high school project I&#39;ve worked on.
This project took a fair bit of work and was probably the first Python program I wrote that I was genuinely proud of, even if it doesn&#39;t stand up compared to some of my other work nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>WiFi Deauthenticator</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2017/06/10/wifi-deauth/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2017/06/10/wifi-deauth/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;So... why did you make this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever seen a project on the internet so interesting that you knew you had to recreate it? That is literally the only reason I made this project. I saw a YouTube tutorial showing off how to make a $5 &amp;quot;wifi jammer&amp;quot; device and I was immediately interested in it. I wasn&#39;t interested in using it for anything actually nefarious, but I did want to play around with it a bit just to know that it was &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I&#39;m being honest, this project isn&#39;t too interesting. It basically boils down to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy an ESP8266&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Program it to disrupt WiFi networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And that&#39;s it...?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really wish there was more to say about this project, but there isn&#39;t. I successfully purchased an ESP8266 board, successfully flashed it with the software, and successfully created a device that could send deauthentication frames to nearby WiFi networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also should clarify that despite me building this device, I never actually used it for anything malicious. I have a habit (and still do to this day) of becoming intrigued with projects with massive potential for chaos, building/designing them, and then never unleashing them because it goes against my better judgement. I think it&#39;s more about interest than any sort of malice or intent to use them, but beyond that I cannot explain why I was so interested in a project I ultimately had no intention of using.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The PRISM</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/posts/2015/06/15/prism/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/posts/2015/06/15/prism/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should preface this project with a bit of context to describe &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; this project was so significant to me. When I created this project, I was 14 years old. Prior to this project, I had no experience with non-software projects. I started programming around the age of 10, because I developed an interest in learning how to make video games. Every pure software project I did at this time was somehow motivated by gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around this time I had started to develop an interest in game emulation. I was fascinated with all of these historic video game titles that had come out before my time, and I wanted to give them a try. Around this time there was plenty of good emulation programs freely available on the internet. However, I believe it was a YouTube video I stumbled across all those years ago that introduced me to the Raspberry Pi, and more importantly at the time, the RetroPie project. There was just something about the idea of having an all-in-one games console that could play games from all sorts of generations of game systems that was extremely appealing to me. To a kid with no other exposure to emulation, the idea of a &amp;quot;super console&amp;quot; that could play any video game imaginable sounded like the kind of thing kids would dream about. In retrospect, it&#39;s no surprise that once I heard about such a project, I &lt;strong&gt;had&lt;/strong&gt; to get my hands on one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so began my journey into the world of Raspberry Pis, and by extension, computer engineering as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project started around the time I discovered the RetroPie project and learned about Raspberry Pi computers as a whole. RetroPie is a special installation of the Raspbian OS for Raspberry Pi single-board computers that lets you turn a Raspberry Pi into a dedicated retro gaming console. This project was fascinating to me, and this is what ultimately led me to buy my first Raspberry Pi. I didn&#39;t care that I could do basically the same thing on my laptop by installing EmulationStation, I just wanted a dedicated console for retro gaming. It didn&#39;t matter if it was practical, &lt;em&gt;it just sounded cool&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is honestly very straightforward and not that impressive from this point onward. I basically ordered a Raspberry Pi 2B, a microSD card and some Logitech F310 gamepads. I installed RetroPie on the SD card, inserted it into the Raspberry Pi and booted it up for the first time. Unsurprisingly, it worked! From there, I got my hands on some ROMs for old games and started playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason this project is of note is because it marks the first hardware-related project I ever attempted, aside from some minor robotics stuff with those Lego Mindstorms kits. It wasn&#39;t too deep into any &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; hardware design since it was literally just buying a computer and programming it, but the important thing is that it included a physical element to a project that I simply had never done before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s normal to be left wondering why I have a section titled &amp;quot;The Aftermath&amp;quot; on what is probably my most innocuous and uninteresting project. The only reason I am including this section is because this project had a surprising impact on my school life after I created it. I brought it into school one day to show it off, as I had been talking to some friends about it. Everyone seemed pretty interested in it, so we found some time to head over to our school&#39;s library to hook it up to the projector and test it out. The librarian was cool with us doing this, and we&#39;d spend our lunch breaks playing some retro video games together in the library which was a lot of fun. Over time, the word about this project got out and people started talking about us. If I&#39;m being totally honest, it got way more attention than what was warranted. It was literally just a Raspberry Pi and a program that I installed on it, but I guess no one else really knew about that part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was this one group of visitors (I do not know exactly &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they came or what their official title would even be) our school had that were coming from another city, and a number of students were putting together presentations for them to show off some of the cool projects that the students were involved in. My homeroom teacher basically forced me into this, so I had to present in front of them. The project was pretty well received, although I could tell they weren&#39;t tech people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I got some school-wide attention for the PRISM as well. At my school, we would always hold an end-of-year assembly to summarize how the school year went. In the past couple of years, they started giving away these awards to a small handful (about half a dozen) students who were &amp;quot;exceptional&amp;quot; at something. These topics ranged from things like creativity, community engagement and so on. I discovered that the invention of this project led to me winning the &amp;quot;Innovation&amp;quot; award at my school, which I thought was pretty neat. I think that the positive feedback I got for this project, even if debatably unwarranted, definitely encouraged me to explore more hardware-focused projects in the future. I think it&#39;s safe to say that while this project wasn&#39;t substantial on its own, it had a pretty large impact on the direction that I would take in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, about the name: the &amp;quot;PRISM&amp;quot;. I think it was an acronym but I cannot remember what it stood for. Probably something cringe to be honest, but I don&#39;t know. I suspect I just wanted a cool-sounding acronym and came up with the actual name afterwards, and &amp;quot;PRISM&amp;quot; must have been the best I could come up with at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>